<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The last sermon of Mr. Joseph Stephens late lecturer of St. Giles's Cripplegate, St. Margaret's Loth-bury, and St. Michael's Woodstreet. Together with I. A sermon compos'd by him a little before his death, (but never preach'd, being prevented by his last sickness.) II. A sermon concerning the hopes of the righteous at death. III. A sermon of Jam. IV. verse 17th; Therefore to him that knoweth to do good, and doth it not, to him it is sin. Lately preachd at the said lectures. All publish'd from his own manuscript copies, fairly written out for the press by himself.</title>
            <author>Stevens, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61479</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5497D</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220100</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831529</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35992</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61479)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35992)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2046:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The last sermon of Mr. Joseph Stephens late lecturer of St. Giles's Cripplegate, St. Margaret's Loth-bury, and St. Michael's Woodstreet. Together with I. A sermon compos'd by him a little before his death, (but never preach'd, being prevented by his last sickness.) II. A sermon concerning the hopes of the righteous at death. III. A sermon of Jam. IV. verse 17th; Therefore to him that knoweth to do good, and doth it not, to him it is sin. Lately preachd at the said lectures. All publish'd from his own manuscript copies, fairly written out for the press by himself.</title>
                  <author>Stevens, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for H. Walwyn at the Three Leggs in the Poultry, against the Stocks-Market,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a preliminary advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>The second, third and fourth sermons have divisional half titles; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Guildhall Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  James IV, 17 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="publishers_notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:2"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>AN Expoſition on the <hi>Lord's-Prayer,</hi> in ſeveral Sermons, Preach'd by the Reverend Mr. <hi>Joſeph Stephens,</hi> Late Lecturer of St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s <hi>Cripplegate,</hi> St. <hi>Margaret</hi>'s <hi>Lothbury,</hi> and St. <hi>Michael</hi>'s <hi>Woodſtreet.</hi> Prepared for the Preſs by himſelf in his Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time. <hi>Very neceſſary for all Perſons and Families, inſtructing them how to pray to God in an acceptable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> Will ſpeedily be Publiſh'd and Printed for <hi>H. Walwyn</hi> at the <hi>Three Leggs</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> againſt the <hi>Stocks-Market.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Laſt Sermon</hi> OF Mr. <hi>Joſeph Stephens,</hi> Late LECTURER of St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s <hi>Cripplegate,</hi> St. <hi>Margaret</hi>'s <hi>Loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> and St. <hi>Michael</hi>'s <hi>Woodſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with
<list>
                  <item>I. A Sermon Compos'd by him a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before his Death, (but never Preach'd, being prevented by his Laſt Sickneſs.)</item>
                  <item>II. A Sermon concerning <hi>The Hopes of the Righteous at Death.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. A Sermon on <hi>Jam.</hi> IV. Verſe 17th; <hi>Therefore to him that knoweth to do good, and doth it not, to him it is ſin.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Lately Preach d at the ſaid Lectures. All Publiſh'd from his own Manuſcript Copies, fairly Written out for the Preſs by himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Walwyn</hi> at the <hi>Three Leggs</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> againſt the <hi>Stocks-Market.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:3"/>
            <head>To the HEARERS of Mr. <hi>Joſeph Stephens,</hi> Late LECTURER at St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s <hi>Cripplegate,</hi> St. <hi>Margaret</hi>'s <hi>Loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> and St. <hi>Michael</hi>'s <hi>Woodſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE following Sermons having the Late Reverend Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> for their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, need not an Epiſtle to recommend them: To You eſpecially, it is needleſs, who are ſo well acquainted with his Worth, and who at this time labour under the heavy ſenſe of your great loſs of him. And indeed in the Age we live in, a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> who is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defatigable in his Endeavours after
<pb facs="tcp:35992:4"/>the ſpiritual good of his <hi>Flock,</hi> ought not to be parted with without a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern as ſingular as his Example is rare. And I am ſure the <hi>Subject</hi> of your ſorrow will juſtify the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree</hi> of it; for ſuch an one was Mr. <hi>Stephens;</hi> One who had an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable Love for the Souls of Men, and for yours in particular; a Love which laſts longer than his Life; for when he had ſpent <hi>that</hi> in your Service, and the time was come that be muſt <hi>Depart hence,</hi> and be your <hi>Lecturer no more:</hi> He did (by ordering his Works to be Printed) as it were, Multiply himſelf among you; for whereas <hi>before</hi> you had him only teaching you from the <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit,</hi> you may now every one [of you] have him <hi>home</hi> with you, Inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you in your Cloſets at all <hi>Times,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:35992:4"/>and upon all <hi>Occaſions;</hi> ſo that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his Labour upon <hi>Earth</hi> be ceas'd, yet he ſeems to be ſtill teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you from <hi>Heaven,</hi> and ſhewing you the ſteps by which he went thither.</p>
            <p>'Twas obſerved, that when he preach'd this his <hi>Laſt Sermon,</hi> he urg'd it with a more than ordinary Warmth, as if he had known it to be the laſt he ſhould utter; for which reaſon it is publiſh'd firſt (before his other Excellent Diſcourſes and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons) that ſo if he had any peculiar drift in the Choice of the Subject, or the home Application of it with reſpect to that Circumſtance of Time (which I am apt to think he had) we might further his intentions, and leave the Effect to Providence. Herewith is alſo Publiſh'd another Sermon which he compoſed a little before he Dyed,
<pb facs="tcp:35992:5"/>(but never Preach'd, being diſabled by his laſt Sickneſs.) Together with his Diſcourſe concerning <hi>the Hopes of the Righteous at Death:</hi> And another on <hi>Jam. 4. 17th</hi> Verſe; <hi>Therefore to him that knoweth to do good, and doth it not, to him it is Sin.</hi> All which, for the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they bear to each other, and the Importance and Seaſonableneſs of their Doctrine, were thought fit to be printed together.</p>
            <p>And to Conclude; May you ſo Regulate your Lives by the Rules he gave you (as it is alſo the Doctrine of Chriſt) that neither theſe, nor any other of his Works hereafter to be Publiſh'd, may Riſe up as Witneſs againſt you at the laſt Day, is the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend and Servant,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35992:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOB XXVII. 5, 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Till I die, I will not remove my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity from me. My righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I hold faſt, and will not let it go: my heart ſhall not reproach me ſo long as I live.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THESE words were ſpoken by <hi>Job,</hi> who here makes a ſolemn Reſolution to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an unprejudiced Mind, and an innocent Conſcience; to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have himſelf prudently, and not to be guilty of that thing wittingly, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y choice, which ſhould either ſhame him to reflect upon, or ſlur his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, were it expoſed to human knowledge. It was in the midſt of
<pb facs="tcp:35992:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35992:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:35992:7"/>Adverſity, and depth of Diſgrace, when he thus covenanted with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; when his Wealth and Store were taken from him, his Children ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted away, and his Servants deſpiſed, and his Friends ſtood at a diſtance from him; when he was tormented with Pains and Sores, and had not where to lay his Head. In the midſt of ſuch an unhappy change of things it was, that this good Man perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily reſolved to keep a Conſcience void of offence towards God, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Man. <hi>As God liveth,</hi> ſays he, Verſe 2. <hi>who hath taken away my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and the Almighty, who hath vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my ſoul: All the while my breath is in me, and the ſpirit of God is in my noſtrils; My lips ſhall not ſpeak of wickedneſs, nor my tongue utter deceit.</hi> Though it were my Lot, and God's determinate Will, that I be thus ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely dealt with all my Days; yet it ſhall be my care and ſtudy to behave my ſelf wiſely in a perfect
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35992:7"/>way; neither to murmur under ſuch Diſpenſations, or do that thing which may ſtain my Integrity, or expoſe me to humane Cenſure. <hi>Till I die, I will not remove my integrity from me. My righteonſneſs I hold faſt, and will not let it go: my heart ſhall not reproach me ſo long as I live.</hi> A well-diſciplin'd Chriſtian's care is, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch a temper of Mind with him out of this World, which may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hance his Happineſs, and improve his Felicity in the next. Therefore it is, that he Debates and Argues, Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines and Judges before he be tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Intereſt or Example. Neither the proſpect of Wealth or Honour, or any worldly Advancement, ſhall induce him to a low-ſpirited Action, or put him upon unjuſt Ways. He ſubmits to the Government of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and does not ſeem to haſten a change of things by immoderate Wiſhes and Deſires. In fine, in the whole Courſe of his Actions he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35992:8"/>a well-pleaſed Conſcience; and will rather forego all External Goods, than forfeit that which will be a continual comfort to him, though in the depth of Diſgrace, and worldly Debaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For what outward Evils can, in a ſenſe, diſturb that Man, who is perpetually followed with a harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Mind, which always reſounds to him thoſe beſt and ſweeteſt Ecchoes, <hi>Well done good and faithful ſervant;</hi> how bravely doſt thou acquit thy ſelf; how manfully doſt thou reſiſt Temptations; what care doſt thou take in the management of thy Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; how little art thou influenced by Intereſt and Example; how cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageouſly doſt thou bear up againſt the Flatteries of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil? <hi>O, well is thee, and happy ſhalt thou be. This,</hi> ſays the Wiſeman, <hi>is a continual feaſt;</hi> and will bear a Man up under all the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties, diſappointments, conflicts, and miſeries of this Life. He need
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35992:8"/>not reſort to Drink or Company to repleniſh his Mind, and relax his Thoughts, who is thus careſſed and crowned with the pleaſing Ecchoes of an unprejudic'd Spirit. This was Holy <hi>Job</hi>'s Conſolation during his Exilement from Proſperity, while his Fleſh groaned under a ſad Cataſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe, and diſmal Change of Things. Upon a review of his Life paſt, he diſcovered that he had walked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly with God; that amidſt all the Temptations which Wealth and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune could careſs him with, he had a ſpecial regard to the thing that was juſt; and though Providence was pleaſed to alter his Condition, and ſtrip him of all External Goods, yet this was his Comfort, <hi>My righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I hold faſt, I have hitherto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained my integrity,</hi> and am reſolved, through the Aſſiſtance of Divine Grace, <hi>that my heart ſhall not reproach me ſo long as I live.</hi> Now my deſign from theſe words, is,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35992:9"/>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt</hi> of all, To ſhew the Neceſſity of Holy Reſolution, wherewith <hi>Job</hi> fortifies himſelf againſt the very worſt that may happen to him, <hi>Till I die, I will not remove my integrity from me;</hi> and ſo on.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> To ſhew how far Holy Reſolution is virtuous, and in what ſenſe it turns to a good account.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To lay down ſome Motives to reſolve well and timely. And then conclude.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt</hi> then, I am to ſhew the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of (Holy Reſolution) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>Job</hi> fortifies himſelf againſt the very worſt that may happen to him, ſaying, in the Text, <hi>Till I die, I will not remove my integrity from me.</hi> We all well know by experience, that we are naturally depraved by the Preſumption and Fall of our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; our Inclinations are vile and propenſe to Evil, our Wills ſtubborn
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35992:9"/>and irregular, our Paſſions violent and mutinous. In fine, in us, that is, in our Fleſh, dwelleth no good thing at all. What Motions to Evil do we ever and anon perceive ſtirred up within us? How greedy are our Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites of the forbidden Fruit? What abundance of unbecoming Thoughts invade our Minds, and invelop our Spirits in Hurry and Confuſion? How naturally averſe are we from Holy Things? How diſagreeable is Duty to our Affections? In a word, how unſuitable is the knowledge of God and another World to us in our Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral State? When a Good preſents it ſelf, and uſes forcible Arguments to court our Acceptance, how apt are we to boggle and protract, to make excuſes, or to give a flat denial? Nay, ſo unhappy are we, that interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively we take more pains to damn, than to ſave our ſelves. For what a deal of our time do we waſte in catering for our Luſts? What Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35992:10"/>and Hardſhips do we rub through to gratify our fooliſh Appetites? How many reſtleſs Nights, and broken Sleeps, do we patiently endure, to bring an unmanly project to bear? In fine, what a train of tumultuous Noiſes will we charge through, to oblige a fond Humour, and anſwer a whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Diſpoſition? This is our Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Nature, this our Unhappineſs through the Tranſgreſſion of our Firſt Parents.</p>
            <p>But this is not all. As we are thus interrupted by our own corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo we are in as much danger by Temptations from without. The Devil, who is rendred for ever inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Repentance, as ſinning with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Tempter, envies the hopeful Condition of Man, who is admitted to Sorrow and Pardon through the Merits and Satisfaction of a Saviour; And therefore uſes all his Art and Cunning to ſtain his Innocence, and to bring him into the ſame miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35992:10"/>Condition with himſelf. He has Apples to pleaſe thoſe of tender, and Gold to enchant thoſe of riper Years; he has Kingdoms to allure the Ambitious, and flattering Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to betray the Pretenders to Reaſon. The Apoſtle gives this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of him, <hi>That he goes up and down like a roaring lion, ſeeking whom he may devour;</hi> and whom he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts us <hi>to reſiſt ſtedfaſt in the Faith.</hi> He examines and obſerves Mens Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and then ſuits his Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons proportionably. He well knew that <hi>Cain</hi> was Proud, Ambitious, and Self-conceited, and by degrees in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced him to imbrue his Hands in the Innocent Blood of his Brother <hi>Abel.</hi> He knew that <hi>Peter</hi> was fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and puſillanimous, and ſo tempted him to deny his Maſter with Oaths and Curſes. He knew that <hi>Judas</hi> was ſelfiſh and covetous, and therefore prompted him to betay the Holy Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus for thirty pieces of Silver. He
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35992:11"/>is a reſtleſs Enemy, and purpoſes to make all he can as miſerable as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. But this is our happineſs, though he is admitted to tempt, yet he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſorce us to Sin; he lays the bait, but cannot compel us to ſwallow it without our conſent. He importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned our Bleſſed Saviour to caſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf down from the Pinacle of the Temple, but was not impowered to do him the miſchief. When we ſtain our Innocence, and loſe our Peace, the blame lies at our own Door; the Adverſary is not ſo much in fault: It is true, he uſed Arguements, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated cloſely, and left no means unattempted; but it was yet in our choice whether we would hearken to, and be overcome by his Allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. — Nor can we lay the blame upon God in ſuffering us to fall, but upon our ſelves, for living careleſs and ſecure, and giving the Enemy fair opportunities and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of committing a Rape up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35992:11"/>our Integrity. <hi>Let no man,</hi> ſays St. <hi>James, ſay, when he is tempted, I am tempted of God, for God cannot be tempted with Evil, neither tempteth he any man. But every man is tempted, when he is drawn away of his own luſt, and inticed,</hi> James 1.13, 14. Were we but ſolicitous and thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, aware of the Adverſary, ſenſible of our own weakneſſes, and furniſhed with wiſe Conſiderations, we ſhould not be ſo eaſily courted to loſe our Innocence, nor would Temptations have ſuch Influence upon us. St. <hi>Paul</hi> in this Caſe thus exhorts us, Epheſ. 6.13, 14, &amp;c. <hi>Wherefore take unto you the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to withſtand in the evil day, and having done all to ſtand. Stand there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, having your loins girt about with truth, having on the breaſt-plate of righteouſneſs, and your feet ſhod with the preparation of the goſpel of peace. Above all, taking the ſhield of faith, wherewith you will be able to quench
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35992:12"/>all the fiery darts of the devil, and take the helmet of ſalvation, and the ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God.</hi> But conſidering, I ſay, our natural Depravation, whereby we are ſtrongly propenſe to Evil, and averſe from that which is Good, are lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Incurſions of Satan, and in imminent danger of falling as ſo many Victims to him; what neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity is there of Holy Reſolution: that ſeeing we are ſet in the midſt of ſo many and great Temptations, we forthwith wiſely reſolve to uſe our utmoſt care and diligence to ſtem the tide of our evil Inclinations with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and to confront the inſinuating Arguments of Temptations without us; <hi>To hold faſt our righteouſneſs, and not to let our hearts reproach us ſo long as we live.</hi> Which leads me in the ſecond place,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To ſhew how far (Holy Reſolution) is virtuous, and in what
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35992:12"/>ſenſe it turns to a good account. To be religiouſly diſpoſed by fits and girds, to load our ſelves with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Vows and Proteſtations in a melancholly Humour, or when we have taken ſome diſguſt at our Sins; but ſo ſoon as this Mood is over, and our Paſſion allayed, we return to our wonted Extravagances, <hi>like the Dog to his vomit,</hi> and the Sow that is waſhed, <hi>to her wallowing in the mire:</hi> I ſay, to be thus uncertainly Good, and to reſolve peremptorily upon a ſudden ſurreption or ſurprize, is not an Argument of a virtuous, but of an unconſtant and wavering ſpirit. Many, after a long and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fatigue in purſuit of their Sins, have reſolved upon amendment; but no ſooner a Temptation hath come in their way, which pleaſed their Humour, but have forgotten what they ſaid, and ſwallowed the Bait with as much eagerneſs as ever. Some, on their Sick Beds, have bound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35992:13"/>under certain Obligations to become new and better Chriſtians, ſhould they be bleſſed with a recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Health and Strength; but ſo ſoon as they have been able to reliſh a pleaſing Luſt, and comply with a ſuitable Temptation, have baſely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated from their late Promiſe, and ſold their Innocence for a trifle. — True indeed, it is a kind of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to reſolve well, to vow amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Life, to be ſerious and thoughtful ſometimes; but it is much more virtuous to paſs into Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and expreſs our ſincerity by an abſolute and thorough Converſion: And unleſs Holy Promiſes terminate into Pious Practices, they will be ſo far from contributing to our happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that they will appear as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inſtances of our Folly, and induce a crimſon Guilt. How many Spirits are there wandring to and fro in the infernal Shades, who, while they were in this Life, made repeated Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35992:13"/>to change their Minds and Manners; and becauſe they did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract and linger, and took no care to pay that which they had vowed, are repenting of their Negligences, and muſt live out a long Eternity in unpitied Sighs and Groans. It is the eaſieſt part of Religion to make fair Promiſes; and did it conſiſt in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, there are but few who would boggle at it: For it is no great difficulty now and then to be ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſed; and during the Mood, to proteſt a Reformation hereafter. That which evidences our Piety, is the mortifying our Luſts and Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſubduing our Wills, and bringing the Fleſh in ſubjection to the Spirit: And without this piece of Religion, all external Pretences are of no ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificancy. If thou voweſt to God, thou doſt well; and if thou makeſt it good, thou doſt better; for he has no pleaſure in the Sacrifice of Fools. — He dates our Converſion from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35992:14"/>that time we have ſlain our Luſts, changed our Minds, ſubdued, our Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, and are reduced to the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of Virtue and a good Nature. Reſolution without practice, is only an argument of a haſty Spirit, of a raſh and injudicious Mind, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders not what he ſays, as well as intends not what he ſolemnly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. But to be more conciſe:</p>
            <p>He that reſolves well, and does not perform, is a Sinner in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree, becauſe he condemns that Courſe of Life he continues in; or otherwiſe, why did he vow to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake it? And let me add, There is leſs hopes of that Man's Converſion who threatneth it by promiſes, but yet protracts and lingers, than of his who never made any; becauſe it plainly argues that his Conſcience is feared, who, notwithſtanding all the Appeals he has made unto God, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution he has confirmed of becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing better, he ſtill continues in his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35992:14"/>Original State, as Vicious, as Senſual as ever. For were he truly affected with a ſenſe of his Condition, were he ſtruck with a thorough Compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for Sin, his Reſoultion would quicken and ſpur him on to deny all Ungodlineſs and worldly Luſt, to live ſoberly and righteouſly. Therefore to ſum up this Head: Holy Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is of no force and validity, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and ſeparate by it ſelf; it car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in it nothing of true Religion unleſs it paſs into Action, and oblige a Man to enter upon ſtrict Diſcipline, to mortify his Paſſions and Luſts, and to proceed in all Virtue and Godlineſs of Living. And he that reckons himſelf in a happy Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe he now and then, in a melancholly penſive Mood, promiſes to become a new Creature, is miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably deceived, and will in the end ſorrowfully find, <hi>That without holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> For when by the mighty Sound of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35992:15"/>laſt Trump we ſhall be awakened, and ſummoned to the dread Tribunal of Chriſt, it will be of no uſe to us, that we many times reſolved to do well; then we ſhall ſtand or fall by our Actions; according to that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtle, <hi>We ſhall all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the judgment-ſeat of Chriſt, to give an account for what we have done in the fleſh, and to receive ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that we have done, whether it be good or bad.</hi> And thus much may ſuffice for the Second thing, which was to ſhew how far (Holy Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) is virtuous, and in what ſenſe it turns to a good Account, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to that of <hi>Job</hi>'s in the Text, ſaying, <hi>Till I die, I will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move my integrity from me. My righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs I hold faſt, and will not let it go; my heart ſhall not reproach me ſo long as I live.</hi> I paſs on now in the third place,</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:35992:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To lay down ſome Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to excite you to reſolve well and timely. And here, <hi>Firſt,</hi> conſider how difficult it is to change a mind that is naturally depraved, and to bring an originally corrupted Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution into a good Frame and Order. For beſides that Sin is innate, born in us, ſo it has been ſpringing up, and growing in our Nature ever ſince our Birth, that it is become head-ſtrong and tumultuous, and requires much Pains and Care, Courage, Reſolution, and Patience, Watchings and Stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, Prayers and Tears to root it out. Sin is not ſoon maſtered; for as it has taken time to gather together, ſo it muſt be the Work of much time to looſen it from its ſtrong holds, and to baniſh it from thence, where it has ſo long continued. Faint Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leities and Puſillanimity will never accompliſh this great Concernment; nor is that Reſolution immediately
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35992:16"/>formed, which can go on with ſuch a painful undertaking. For if there be any leak left open in our Reſolution for any Sin to creep in at, that will be ſure to inſinuate in the next Storm of Temptation; and if it ſhould not let in other Sins after it, as it is a thouſand to one but it will, it will by its own ſingle weight ſink us into Eternal Perdition. Wherefore before we enter into the Reſolution of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we ought to be very careful that our Wills be thoroughly prepared for it, that they be reduced to a fair compliance with the matter we are reſolved upon, and effectually diſſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of all Reſolution to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And when this is done, we may chearfully proceed to the forming of our good Reſolution; or otherwiſe, all is but Heat and Paſſion, irregular Motions of the Mind, which will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver help a Man to encounter with his Luſts, nor hold out till he has reduced himſelf to a fair compliance with the Duties of Religion.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35992:16"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The ſtronger and ſooner we reſolve upon Amendment, the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier and leſs difficult will it be to tame our Paſſions, and extirpate our Luſts; for they are ſtill improving, and every day get more and more ſtrength and ground of us, which if permitted to ſpread and grow up, will at length become ſo tyrannical and tumultuous, ſo radicated and habitual, that we ſhall become Impotent, and it will be in vain to make any Sally upon them. And beſides, the longer it is before we enter into Holy Reſolution, the more liſtleſs and untoward we ſhall be to begin a Work of ſo much time and pains; ſo that, what through our faint-heartedneſs on the one hand, and the difficulties we muſt rub through on the other, before we can change our Natures, and reduce them to the evenneſs of Virtue, we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance die in the interim, and are ſunk by the weight of our own guilt into Eternal Miſery. Therefore as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35992:17"/>we would ſucceed in this great and mighty Concernment, and gain the Victory over our ſelves, as we would not in the latter end of our days have ſuch a troubleſome Work to begin, when we ſhall have the leaſt Strength and Courage to carry it on; let us be ſo wiſe for our ſelves, to enter upon a ſerious Reſolation timely, when both our Years, and the Youth of our Luſts, promiſe us the Victory over them. But why ſo much admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this Caſe? Why ſuch need of Argument to preſs to ſuch a Temper of Mind, when our Souls lie at ſtake, whoſe Eternal Happineſs or Miſery depends upon our good or bad Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of them. And if we loſe them, we loſe our All, and no poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of recovering them. As our Saviour ſays, <hi>What can a man give in exchange for his ſoul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſider what a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Condition that Man is in, who
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35992:17"/>by aſſiduous Watchings and Strivings, Prayers and Tears, by wiſe Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and ſtrenuous Arguments, has ſubdued his Luſts, and reduced the Senſual to a fair compliance with the Rational Part; what ſlavery and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, what Perturbations and Tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Noiſes is he freed from? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he that is ſubſervient to his irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Appetite, is at the beck of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Motion; hurried on from one Evil to another, fatiegued and worried by an injuried Mind, and is never at peace from the reſtleſs Importunities of his craving Luſts. What miſchieſs is he daily expoſed to? And what baſe and unmanly Shifts is he put upon to extricate himſelf out of thoſe Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties he involves himſelf? How does his Luſts perplex and intriegue the whole Courſe of his Life, and intangle him in a Labyrinth of knaviſh Tricks and Colluſions? But he that by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Arts and Strengths of Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion has gained the aſcendent over
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35992:18"/>his Nature, is never thus interrupted, nor expoſed to ſuch Actions, which he ſhall either be aſhamed to own, or care if they were manifeſt to the whole World. He is no longer go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by blind Paſſion, but directed by right Reaſon; he is not influenced by Intereſt or Example, unleſs it be warrantable, and becomes a Chriſtian. And now upon the whole,</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, I think there cannot be any thing more argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentative, nor of more force to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with rational Men to enter upon Holy Reſolution, ſince it produces ſuch happy Effects. And as it will certainly carry us ſafe through a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome and noiſy World, ſo it quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies us for the Enjoyments and Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of a far better; where we ſhall recount with Triumph and Glory, with what courage and bravery we acquitted our ſelves, how manfully we reſiſted the Impulſes of the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35992:18"/>part; how reſolutely we ſtemm'd the Tide of our Evil Inclinations, and gave a defiance to the ſtrongeſt Temptations; how chearfully we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevered, though we met with almoſt immovable Impediments, and retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>our integrity as long as we lived.</hi> And by all this, our Love and Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhown to God; then ſhall we tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph for ever with the glorious Company of the Apoſtles, the goodly Fellowſhip of the Prophets, and the noble Army of Martyrs, with all the Saints and Servants of God. To which Happineſs God of his abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Mercy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:19"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:19"/>
            <head>THE SECOND SERMON.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:20"/>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:35992:20"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PHIL. III. 13, 14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Brethren, I count not my ſelf to have apprehended; but this one thing I do, forgetting thoſe things which are behind, and reaching forth to thoſe things which are before, I preſs toward the mark, for the prize of the high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THESE Words ſeem to be a caution given by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle againſt the falſe Teachers ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion about Perfection in this State, from the inſtance of himſelf, ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently called to be an Ambaſſador
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35992:21"/>for Chriſt. There were ſome who inſinuated, That it was poſſible to arrive at ſuch a Degree of Goodneſs in this Life, that perſons might ſtop there, without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther improvement, and without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hazard of loſing their Reward. This abſurd opinion the Apoſtle endeavours to confute; and from himſelf ſhews, That he did not think he was ſo ſure of the Crown, that he could not miſs it. I, ſays he, conſider not how much of my Race I have run, what Virtues I have attained, what Proficiency I have made in the Chriſtian War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare; my buſineſs is, while I have Life, and the uſe of my Faculties, to be ſtill aiming at more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent degrees of Perfection in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. I count not my ſelf to have apprehended, I am not ſo good as I may and ought to be; nor ſhall the time paſt which I have ſpent in gathering together the Chriſtian
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35992:21"/>Graces, ſuffice for the time to come; but that alſo ſhall be employed in holy Exerciſes, in watchings and ſtrivings, in earneſt prayers, and wiſe conſiderations; I will ſtill be running my Race, till I come to the very Goal; <hi>forgetting thoſe things which are behind, and reaching forth to thoſe things which are before, I preſs toward the mark, for the prize of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> While we are on this ſide the Grave, we are continually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to Temptations; and by ſad Experience we find, that they too often inſinuate with, and prevail over us, ſometimes by ſudden ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reption or ſurprize, ſometimes for want of a good judgment and a ſound underſtanding; and ſometimes for want of ſubſtantial Arguments and ſutable Conſiderations; ſo that ſtill here is work for Repentance, and a renewed Obligation upon us, to grow ſtronger and ſtronger in the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35992:22"/>Lord, and in the power of his might. Virtue is like unto Steel, if it be diſuſed, will loſe its luſtre, and contract a ruſt; if thoſe Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces we have acquired, be not exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, and improved, they will ſoon faint and languiſh, and leave us to the mercy of every Temptation; for it is not ſufficient that we are juſt emerged and recovered out of a ſinful ſtate, that by holy reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and much labour we have cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected our evil Inclinations and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, and are juſt gotten over the line that parts a good and bad ſtate: For beſides that, the line which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parates theſe two ſtates of Sin and Grace is not ſo eaſily diſcerned, but that we may in all likelihood be deceived, and imagine that we are happily gotten over into a ſafe condition, while we are bordering upon the brink of our Original State, and ſo may at laſt ſuffer Shipwreck at the mouth of our Harbour; I
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:35992:22"/>ſay, beſides this, it is a ſhrewd ſign that we are yet in our Sins, that we intend no further than juſt to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our ſelves from that everlaſting ruin which awaits them; which alſo demonſtrates, that the dread of Hell is the very Life and Soul of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and that there is not the leaſt inſtance of the love and fear of God joined with it; without which, all ſeeming pretenſions to Chriſtianity are nothing worth. And further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, while we reſt in ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect ſtate of Goodneſs, we have no ſecurity againſt a Relapſe, but are every moment in danger of returning into our natural ſtate. The Apoſtle therefore, who kept a watchful and a jealous Eye upon the inconſtancy of his nature, who had well ſtudied himſelf, and the accompliſhments of a Chriſtian, who knew the danger of ſtopping at any determinate degrees of Goodneſs, that while he imagined himſelf ſure of a Crown, might by
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35992:23"/>this means at laſt fall ſhort of it. Herein the Text modeſtly cenſures his own inſufficiency, and urges, that it was not enough, that he had by watchings and ſtrivings, by earneſt prayer, and wiſe conſiderations, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his nature, and conquer'd his paſſions; but that he ſtill be impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and aim at the farthermoſt Degree of Perfection in Holineſs. <hi>Brethren,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I count not my ſelf to have apprehended; but this one thing I do, forgetting thoſe things which are behind, and reaching forth to thoſe things which are before: I preſs toward the mark, for the prize of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Which words, as they lie, afford us theſe following Propoſitions:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> That a Chriſtian, while he continues in this Life, muſt not ſtop at any determinate degree in Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, out of a fond conceit that he is good enough already. <hi>I count not
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35992:23"/>my ſelf,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>to have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, and therefore I forget thoſe things which are behind, and reach forth to thoſe things which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> That Perfection, as ſuch, is not attainable in this Life, and therefore we ought to be as good as is poſſible. <hi>I preſs, toward the mark, for the prize of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And Laſtly, That it is very dangerous to ſtop in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian warfare, as being at leiſure to liſten to Temptations, and ſo be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed into our natural ſtate. I ſhall Treat upon theſe in their order.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That a Chriſtian, while he continues in this Life, muſt not ſtop at any determinate degree in Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, out of a fond conceit that he is good enough already; for Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35992:24"/>is every-where in Scripture en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined in unlimited and indefinite terms. We are commanded not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have Grace, but to grow in it; not only to walk in all well-pleaſing to God, but to abound in ſo doing more and more; that is, That we do not limit our ſelves to any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent attainments, out of a ſlothful Opinion that we are Righteous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; but that we aim at more eminent improvements, reach after thoſe things which are before. It is a very abſurd conceit that we are good enough for Heaven, that we have done enough for the attainment of that Reward which God has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed; that we are ſufficiently qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified to dwell among Angels and Saints. For beſides that ſuch a lofty thought of one's ſelf, argues ſpiritual Pride, than which nothing more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to God; ſo it implies, That we conclude our labours meritorious that Heaven is not a Deed of Gift
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35992:24"/>but our proper right; not a Reward of free mercy, but our juſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable claim. Should we but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect what imperfections are min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with the beſt of our Services, how far we fall ſhort of perfect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinning Obedience, how often we ſtain our Innocence, and make work for our Repentance, what ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions there are between Fleſh and Spirit, between our bad Inclinations, and our pious Reſolutions; and how often it is, that ſometimes through natural infirmity, and ſometimes by our own conſent, we are betrayed, and overcome; I ſay, did we but conſider how many indecencies we are guilty of, and what a mixture of evils there is in the beſt of our performances, this were enough to put us out of conceit with our own Goodneſs, and to quicken and ſpur us on to rectify the diſorders of our nature, and to advance yet more and more in the ways of Holineſs;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35992:25"/>and even when we have done all, as our Saviour expreſſes it, we muſt ſay, that <hi>we are unprofitable Servants,</hi> we have done that which was but our duty to do; for alas! God does not exact duty from us becauſe he needs it, becauſe he is the better for it. For (beſides that he cannot want any thing without himſelf, that he cannot any ways need mortal Breath to praiſe him, or hands of Fleſh to ſerve him, who has millions of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Creatures than we, abſolutely at his Devotion, and can with a word create millions of millions more fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than we to honour him) the beſt eſtimation we can have of him is much below him; the beſt expreſſion we can make, is very unworthy of him; he is infinitely excellent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what we can imagine or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare. It is only his pure Goodneſs that moves him, for our benefit and advantage, to demand it of us. He has made Obedience the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35992:25"/>of our happineſs, though the utmoſt we can do, falleth far ſhort of the reward; nor has God ſet any boundary to Holineſs; but enjoins, That we be always abounding in his Work. And alas! What is Finite Service to an Infinite Recompence? A ſhort Life ſpent here in watchings and ſtrivings, in prayers and tears, in mortification and ſtrict diſcipline, to a Life in Heaven, where every Eye ſparkles with joy, every Heart overflows with gladneſs, and every Tongue perpetually is imployed in ſinging the Song of <hi>Moſes</hi> and of the Lamb, where all tears ſhall be wiped from our Eyes, ſhall move in a wide and capacious Sphere, and feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an Happineſs, which is as large as our capacities, and as laſting as our beings. Can we be good enough to dwell for ever with a God, <hi>with whom is no variableneſs nor ſhadow of turning?</hi> is the farthermoſt degree of all poſſible Perfection in Holineſs, to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35992:26"/>be compared with that purity which admits of no abatements? Should he ſtrictly obſerve the indecencies which are in the beſt of our performances, or thoſe petulant follies we are guilty of, when in a converted and rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate ſtate, they were enough by their own weight to ſink us into Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Perdition. So that, conſidering how defective we are at beſt, there is work enough for Repentance, and for the Exerciſing of Chriſtian Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſo long as we live. It is not ſuch an eaſy thing to change an evil mind, to correct a rude nature, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our ſelves againſt a Relapſe; for this it ſeems is our unhappineſs, <hi>the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh, ſo that we cannot do the things that we would,</hi> Galat. 5.17. While we are in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, we ſhall meet with difficulties and oppoſitions, occaſioned by the Fleſh warring againſt the Spirit, and oſtentimes we are put to it to keep
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35992:26"/>our integrity, and too frequently, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſurprize, or for want of a good Judgment, or ſubſtantial Arguments, and ſuitable Conſiderations, we fall, and make work for our Repentance; and this is the buſineſs of our whole lives, to repent as ſoon as we have ſlipped, and to fortify our ſelves with the whole Armour of God againſt Temptations. But thus much for the firſt propoſition; namely, That a Chriſtian, while he continues in this Life, muſt not ſtop at any determinate degree in Holineſs, out of a fond conceit that he is good enough already. From this I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the Second Propoſition; which is</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That (Perfection) as ſuch, is not attainable in this Life, and therefore we ought to ſtrive to be as good as is poſſible. <hi>I count not my ſelf,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>to have apprehended; but this one thing I do,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35992:27"/>forgetting thoſe things which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, and reaching forth to thoſe things which are before; I preſs toward the mark, for the prize of the high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> To be perfect, in a ſtrict ſenſe, is to be free from imbecility, whether natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, or contracted; from any ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, or appearance of inſirmity; in fine, it implies ſuch an advancement, which admits of no degree beyond it, when a Chriſtian, by ſpecial arts has furniſhed himſelf with ſuch a Complication of Graces, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not err, nor be in danger of falling; now it is impoſſible, while our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are clogged with Fleſh, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the infirmities of human nature, to be thus compleat and ſpotleſs; for even the beſt of men, by ſad experience find how imperfect and weak they are, how apt to fall; that to regain their innocence are forced to renew their ſorrows. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly we read one of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35992:27"/>Proficients in the School of Chriſt, lamenting the corruption of his nature, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from the body of this death?</hi> Some of the Ancients call this Verſe, <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus ſanctorum,</hi> the groan, or lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of good Chriſtians, who are troubled at heart, that they are ſo much interrupted by the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of the Fleſh, that they cannot ſerve God with better attention, with that ſtrictneſs of Zeal, and ardency of Affection, they would. For what through the prevalency of the Fleſh, and the ſubtle, but almoſt incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable inſinuations of the common Adverſary, they are ſometimes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to holy duties, diſturbed by a multitude of unbecoming thoughts when engaged in them; ſend up their prayers with cold deſires, are more inſenſible of their ſpiritual wants, are ſometimes more inclinable to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with a temptation, and are at
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35992:28"/>a loſs for Arguments to preſerve their innocence; theſe unhappineſſes, and many more, too tedious to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, attending the beſt of men, are as ſo many incentives to Repentance, to quicken and ſpur them on in watchings and ſtrivings; theſe oblige them to keep a jealous Eye upon the inconſtancy of their nature, and to be ſtill furniſhing themſelves with wiſe conſiderations, that they may regulate their infirmities, and reduce themſelves to a better compliance with the duties of Religion. The condition of nature is ſuch, that as long as we are in the World, we ſhall be courted by temptations to loſe our innocence; and though we have by hearty endeavours ſtemmed the Tyde of our evil inclinations, and made our Wills corrective and governable, ſo that temptations are not ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, nor we in ſuch manifeſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being deluded by them; yet oftentimes on a ſudden, not being
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:35992:28"/>immediately upon our guard, we are inſenſibly betrayed, and make freſh work for our Repentance. <hi>Peter</hi> little thought when he told our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, that <hi>he would die with him before he would deny him,</hi> that ever he ſhould have been guilty of ſuch a diſingenuous act; yet no ſooner was he put to proof, but he degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from his ſo ſolemn a promiſe; and accordingly we read him a weeping for what he had done, nay, bitterly, that he who was ſuch an eminent Apoſtle, had made ſo great a progreſs in holy Diſcipline, ſhould ſtain his innocence, and loſe his peace. In fine, while Fleſh and Spirit are joined together, there will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and war, and during that, it is impoſſible to be void of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and infirmities. Says St. <hi>Paul,</hi> here <hi>we ſee as through a glaſs darkly,</hi> here <hi>we know but in part;</hi> in this Life, at beſt, we are frail defective Creatures; but in another World we
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35992:29"/>we ſhall ſee more clearly; there the infirmities of humane nature will be done away, all temptation to ſin ſhall ceaſe, nothing ſhall interrupt us in our devotion, nor call us off from our enjoyments: then the tempter, who now has permiſſion to uſe arguments, and lay his baits, ſhall be confined in the Priſon of Hell for ever, and ſhall never betray or hurt us more. But while we are in this ſtate, through the interruption of the fleſh, we are mainly hindered, ſo that we cannot do the things which we would. And in regard that ſuch is our unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, we muſt not limit our ſelves to any preſent attainments, ſtop at any determinate degree in Holineſs, out of a fond conceit, that we are good enough already, but follow the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle's example, who thus ſpeaks of himſelf; <hi>I count not my ſelf to have apprehended; but this one thing I do, forgetting thoſe things which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, and reaching forth to thoſe things
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35992:29"/>which are before: I preſs toward the mark, for the prize of the high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> But I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to the Third and Laſt Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That it is dangerous to make a ſtop in the Chriſtian war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, out of a fond conceit that we are good enough already, as being at leiſure to liſten to Temptations, and ſo be betrayed into our firſt and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural State. For as it argues the being weary of well-doing, that we begin to be cloyed with Virtue and ſtrict Diſcipline, are tired out by Watchings and Strivings, when we thus ſlacken our pace in the Chriſtian warfare, and only entertain our ſelves with the conſideration how much of our race we have run, and are contented with what we have already done; ſo we give the faireſt advantage imaginable for Temptations to inſinuate with, and the Devil to exerciſe his Arts
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35992:30"/>upon us. A Self-conceited Chriſtian is a fair invitation to him; nor can he have a better proſpect of ſucceſs, than when he finds a Man puffed up with an over-weaning Confidence of his own ſtrength. For then ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he works upon him by a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſurreption or ſurprize, as being not thoughtfully diſpoſed, nor in a watchful poſture; ſometimes again he inſinuates with, and prevails upon him, he not having his Mind furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with wiſe Conſiderations. He that once begins to abate his Endeavours, to diſuſe that ſtrict diſcipline he was wont to exerciſe himſelf under, to admit of larger allowances, and to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelf to preſent attainments, will go back much faſter than ever he went forward; for thoſe Vertues he has acquired, being not conſtantly exerciſed, will by degrees grow weak and faint, and at length terminate into final Apoſtacy. And beſides this, it is juſt with God to ſuffer ſuch a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35992:30"/>one finally to miſcarry, who has been ſo long taking Heaven by ſtorm and violence, has broken through ſo many oppoſitions to come at it, and in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite of all the darts of temptation from without, and of all the weights and preſſures of inclination from within, was gotten up as it were to the top of the Scaling Ladder, had laid his hands on the Battlements of Heaven, and was ready to leap in, and take poſſeſſion of the joys of it; and at laſt ſlackens his hold, abates his induſtry, and ſits down ſecure and careleſs; I ſay, it is juſt with God to permit ſuch a one to fall, and that finally: That after the bleſſed Spirit has cultivated his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and planted it with Vertues, he unravels his Workmanſhip, and turns his growing <hi>Sharon</hi> into a barren Wilderneſs. Thus we ſee how dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous it is to ſtop at any deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate degree in goodneſs, out of a fond conceit that we are good
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:35992:31"/>enough already, that we are liable to relapſe into our former ſtate, and ſhall plunge our ſelves into a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable condition. The Apoſtle there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſely conſidered this, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to be ſtill advancing more and more in the Chriſtian War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare. <hi>I count not my ſelf,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to have apprehended,</hi> or either were already perfect; but I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after, if that I may appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that, for which alſo I am apprehended of Chriſt Jeſus; <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting thoſe things which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, and reaching forth to thoſe things which are before: I preſs toward the mark, for the prize of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I now proceed to draw ſome uſeful and practical Inferences from what hath been ſaid, and ſo conclude. And here,</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:35992:31"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> If this Life be a time of Trial and probation, wherein God has appointed much work to be finiſhed by us; let us forthwith ſet our ſelves about it, eſpecially conſidering how uncertain our ſtay is here. Let us never abate our endeavours, nor ſlacken our diligence out of a fond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit that we are good enough already, leſt we finally miſcarry. It is not enough that we correct the indecencies of our natures, and ſtem the Tide of our evil inclinations; that we forſake our Sins, and hate them; but that we alſo attain all the Chriſtian Vertues and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and theſe to grow and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, by exerciſing them about their proper Object, even God. Now this is not a fatigue to be accompliſhed on a ſudden; it is not an eaſy thing to make an evil mind comply with a Vertue; here muſt be many Strifes and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35992:32"/>Contentions, ſtrong Diſputes, and ſhrewd Arguings, before our ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Wills can be brought to a fair compliance with a Chriſtian Grace; and then here muſt be great induſtry uſed to digeſt it into habit and Cuſtom, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is ſooner loſt, than it was gained. And then, conſidering the many Temptations from without us, which are continually inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting us by their reſtleſs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, it is very difficult to retain a Vertue, after a long and tedious purſuit after it; and the caſe being ſo, this will keep us for ever ſufficiently Employed, and oblige us to Eternity to be ſtill aſpiring beyond our preſent At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Nor is there the want of Encouragement, to ſpur us on in the Chriſtian Warfare. The Reward far exceeds our Labour,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:35992:32"/>will make us amends for the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worſt we can undergo. What is it to ſpend a few days or years in ſtriving and contending with our inclinations; in Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Watchfulneſs, in Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Prayer and Severe Refiections on our ſelves, when we are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured before-hand, that at the End of this ſhort conflict, we ſhall be carried off by Angels in Triumph into Heaven, and there receive from the Captain of our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a Crown of Everlaſting Joys and Pleaſures; when after a few moments Pains and Labour, we ſhall live Millions of moſt happy. Ages, in the raviſhing fruition of a boundleſs Good? I ſay, Who that conſiders what great things God has prepared for them that love him, would boggle at the difficulties in the Chriſtian War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare? Is it not a raviſhing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:35992:33"/>to think, that the time is coming, when we ſhall bathe our dilated Faculties in an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing River of Pleaſures, and feed upon an Happineſs which is as large as our Capacities, and as laſting as our Beings!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let us therefore run with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience the Race that is ſet before us. And may the God of Peace which brought again from the Dead our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the great Shepherd of the Sheep, through the Blood of the Everlaſting Covenant make you perfect in every good Work, to do his Will, Working in you that which is well-pleaſing in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To whom, with the Father and Ever Bleſſed Spirit, be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:35992:33"/>all Honour, Praiſe, Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, and Obedience, now, henceforth, and for Evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:34"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:34"/>
            <head>THE THIRD SERMON.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:35"/>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:35992:35"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. XIV. Latter part of the 32d</hi> verſe.</bibl>
                  <p>But the Righteous lath hope in his Death.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>BESIDES the many Bleſſings which Religion Intitles a good Chriſtian to, while he continues in this Life, ſuch as God's ſpecial Favour and Protection, Succeſs to his Endeavours, a reputable Name, and ſuch like; there is yet one eminent advantage which it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces at the laſt gaſp, as our Wiſe man obſerves in the Text; and that is, a ſolid Hope and Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of an Inheritance with the Saints in Light, an aſſurance of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:35992:36"/>going to God, and living with him to all Eternity. This was it which ſolaced the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> when under the apprehenſion of an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching and cruel Death, 2 <hi>Ep.</hi> Tim. 4.6. <hi>I am now ready to be offered up, and the time of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture is at hand;</hi> but ſtill this is my Comfort, my Life hath been ſpent in God's Service; <hi>I have fought the good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith;</hi> and therefore I reſt in this, that <hi>henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Lord the Righteous Judge will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon me,</hi> when he comes in the laſt Day, to diſpenſe his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and Puniſhments. It is a ſweet Reflection to a good man, when he is packing up for Eternity, that he made it his care and buſineſs to dreſs his Soul for the embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Father of Spirits; to think that he ſhall bathe his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:35992:36"/>Faculties in an overflowing River of Pleaſures, and feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an Happineſs which is as large as his Capacity, and as laſting as his Being; to think that as ſoon as his Soul is ſtormed out of the outworks of Nature, the Angels, which are miniſtring Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, will convey it into <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Boſom; I ſay, ſuch a thought as this upon a Death-bed, miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates the Ragings of an imperious Diſeaſe, ſweetens the bitter Cup, and renders the approaches of Death leſs formidable and ſcaring. Whereas, when a Wicked man, after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated Provocations, and wilful reſiſtings of Divine Grace, is flung by an inviſible hand upon his Sick or Death-bed; he is preſently Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned by his injured Conſcience, and a large Catalogue of all his Sins is opened and read before him; he is afraid to Dye, becauſe he
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:35992:37"/>has all along lived in Rebellion againſt God. And here we may imagine what a ſurprize the Wretch is in, to think, that he muſt live out a long Eternity in unpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable Sighs and Groans, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the Vengeance of an irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable God; that no ſooner will Death cut the Thread of Life; but he enters into a World of deſpairing Ghoſts; and that at the Day of Judgment, muſt change his unhappy condition for a much worſe; theſe are the Thoughts which uſually attend ungodly men, when they are making their Exit, unleſs they are hardned, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of their ſenſes through the Violence of their Diſtemper. This is the laſt puniſhment of a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious courſe in this Life: And one would think, that ſuch an uncouth remembrance of things, at ſuch a time when a man is under the ill circumſtance of an
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:35992:37"/>intolerable Diſtemper, when Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is almoſt ſpent, the Eyes darkned like a ſullied Mirror, the Face beſmeared with a clammy ſweat, the whole Body trembling under the Severity of death, when the Soul, as it were, ſets hover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Lip, juſt advancing upon the Shoar of another invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible World; I ſay, one would think, that it were enough to make men afraid of Sin, to be thus miſerably tormented with the Reflections of it, when they are ſtepping out of this, into a wide World of Spirits, where their ſorrows will be Augmented, and the remembrance how they have lived here will afflict them more, than to be ſtung with Snakes, whipt with Scorpions, and all the Inſtruments of torture applied un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. And it is no leſs a prevalent Motive to the Study and Practice of Religion, that it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35992:38"/>a man to generous Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to order his Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo, that he ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, nor afraid to look back upon the paſſages of his Life paſt, when he comes to dye; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive his drooping Spirits with the Hope and Aſſurance of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencing a Happy and Joyful E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity; having in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity, not with fleſhly Wiſdom, but by the Grace of God, had his Converſation in the World. And ſo ſays <hi>Solomon</hi> in the Text, <hi>The righteous hath hope in his death;</hi> the conſideration of his well-ſpent Life, lifts him up at the laſt gaſp with the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of living with God, Angels, and Saints. Which words mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly imply this Propoſition <hi>(viz)</hi> That a truly pious and holy Life, produces a happy and comfortable Death.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:35992:38"/>
            </p>
            <p>Now my Buſineſs ſhall be,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> To prove the Truth of this. Then,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> To perſuade Men to the Practice of Religion, from the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, that it brings Peace at the laſt; and qualifies their Souls for the Embraces of the Father of Spirits.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt</hi> then, I am to prove the Truth of this <hi>(viz.)</hi> That a truly Pious and Holy Life produces a Happy and Comfortable Death; which is the ſame in ſenſe and meaning with what the Wiſe-man aſſerts in the Text, <hi>That the Righteous hath hope in his Death;</hi> as if he had ſaid, That man that Exerciſes himſelf daily to <hi>have a Conſcience void of offence towards God, and towards man;</hi> who by Study and ſpecial Arts hath contracted an intire love to God and Religion, and lives in a conſtant and unfeigned Obedience to the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:35992:39"/>of the Goſpel, ſhall be ſo far from having any frightful Reflection upon what is paſt, or diſmal Proſpect of what is to come, at the time of his Death, that the very conſideration of his ſincerity in the Practice of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, will revive and cheer his droop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit, with the Hope and Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of a joyful Reſurrection to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, through the Merits and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of Jeſus Chriſt; by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of whoſe Righteouſneſs, he ſhall be enabled to ſtand blameleſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God. How true this is, our own Experience and Obſervation tells us. When we have viſited a Friend, Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or Relation, who have had their Converſation here in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity, with what cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs have they reſigned to God's Will and Diſpoſal? How little have they been concerned at the Thoughts of approaching Death? With what Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Satisfaction have they looked back upon, and remembred the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:35992:39"/>courſe of their Actions? How have they rejoiced in the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience? How light and eaſy did the Yokes of Pain and Sickneſs ſet upon them, being taken up with the Thoughts of a future happy Life, and Eſtabliſhed with the aſſurance of Reigning the Lives of Victorious Saints? What Lectures of Admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have they delivered to their ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving Acquaintances, that they would live in the fear of God, and dedicate their days to his Service, for that ſuch a Converſation only will bring them peace at the laſt? With what Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage did they meet the King of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors? How familiar and comfortable were his approaches to them, having the ſame mind which was in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>deſirous to be diſſolved, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of ſpending an Eternity with Chriſt,</hi> whoſe Vertues they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to imitate, and whoſe Example they made the Pattern and Model of their Actions? This is the comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:35992:40"/>State and Condition of good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, when lying under the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py circumſtances of Mortal Pains or Sickneſſes; neither the inconvenience of a crazy and diſtempered Body, nor the fear of Death, nor all the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances which uſually attend a death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, can ſhake their Faith, or remove their Hope of a bleſſed Immortality. For the very Deſign and Purpoſe of Religion is, To teach men how to dreſs their Souls for the embraces of the Father of Spirits, to furniſh them with ſuch neceſſary Graces, as may prepare them to ſtand before the Son of Man when he comes to Judgment; and he that is endued with this holy Principle, and by Practice hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted it into habit, has anſwered the great end of his being ſent into the World, and is fortified with conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations ſufficient againſt the worſt that may happen to him. Of ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and gracious Nature is Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that it qualifies a man for all
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:35992:40"/>ſtates and conditions of Life; if he be Rich, it inſtructs him to ſet looſe in his Affections to the Goods and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of this World; not to prefer the Creature to, or bring it in compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition with the Creator; but to uſe this World, as not abuſing it, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately embracing ſublunary Bleſſings; with a generous Reſignation of mind to leave them without murmuring, if Providence ſo ordains it, either to take them from us, or we from them. In fine, Religion alſo learns the Man who is fortunately bleſſed, to be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably diſpoſed, to feed the hungry, to clothe the naked, to miniſter to perſons according to their unhappy circumſtances. If a man be poor, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion teaches him to be content with his Lot, and to ſubmit cheerfully to him that governs the World, who knows what condition is beſt for us; it learns him not to covet the Goods of another; it being a mighty diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance to the Tranquility of the mind,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:35992:41"/>to Deſire, and not to have; it alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs to be honeſtly inclined, by ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining from pilfering and ſtealing, poverty being a ſtrong temptation thereto, without the prevention of Divine Grace. In brief, Religion prompts us to whatſoever things are honeſt, juſt, pure, lovely, and of good Report; and he that by ſpecial arts and ſtrengths of Mortification, has reduced his nature to the evenneſs of Vertue, and a good diſpoſition, has <hi>laid up a good foundation againſt the time to come.</hi> Whenever God ſends his Meſſenger to call him off the Stage of this World, he comforts himſelf as the holy Apoſtle did; <hi>The time of my departure is at hand;</hi> I am now ready to be ſtripped into a naked Spirit, and to lanch into a wide Eternity; but this is my Conſolation; <hi>I have fought the good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, and have kept the Faith;</hi> upon which I ground this aſſurance, That when Chriſt, who is my Life, ſhall appear,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:35992:41"/>I alſo ſhall appear with him in Glory. Whereas, when a man, whoſe Life has been a perpetual courſe of unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted iniquity, comes to dye, with what reluctancy does he ſubmit to the Condition of Nature, and the Will of Providence? What dreadful Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions is his crazy mind infeſted with? What Fears and Amazements does he labour under? Conſcience, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was lulled into a fatal ſlumber, is now awakened, and alarms him with a repetition of his wonted inſolencies, and at once gives him a View of his whole Life; <hi>Theſe things haſt thou done, and I kept ſilence; but I will reprove thee, and ſet all thy ſins in order before thee.</hi> This is but a bad Character to be given of a man by his own Spirit; and the very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of it muſt needs invade his Mind with abundance of ill-aboding Thoughts, and ſcaring Reflections; and the more, becauſe he has no time to recover himſelf by Repentance and
<pb facs="tcp:35992:42"/>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:35992:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:35992:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:35992:44"/>a new Life; he has neither ſtrength nor opportunity to expreſs ſuch ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for his miſcarriages, as may move an offended God to Reconciliation, but muſt leave this World in doubts and fears; and, which he has too much reaſon to believe, muſt endure the deſpair of a damned Ghoſt for ever. This, I ſay, is the ſorrowful conflict of a wicked man upon his death-bed, a ſad Reflection upon what is paſt, and a diſmal Proſpect of what is to come. But it is not ſo with him who has ordered his Converſation aright; he, ſays my Text, <hi>has hope in his death,</hi> that after this painful Life is ended, he ſhall enter into <hi>an houſe not made with hands, whoſe builder and maker is God;</hi> where nothing ſhall interrupt or call him off from his Enjoyments; no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiety ſhall render his fruition loathſom or tedious; but ſhall ſpend a long Eternity in perfect, conſtant, and unmixed Happineſs.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:35992:44"/>
            </p>
            <p>But thus much for the firſt thing; which was, That a truly pious and holy Life, produces a happy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Death, according to the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's aſſertion in the Text, <hi>The righteous has hope in his death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I proceed from hence to the Second thing; which is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To perſuade Men to a Holy and Religious Life, from the conſideration that it brings peace at the laſt, and prepares our Souls for the embraces of the Father of Spirits. And here,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt</hi> of all; Religion does not put a man upon any thing which he ſhall be aſhamed of; but as he is a rational Creature, capable of diſtinguiſhing between Good and Evil, only obliges him to ſuch actions which he may give a good account of to his own Conſcience, and to God, who is greater than his Conſcience. It inſtructs him to chuſe what is good in it ſelf, and to reject
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:35992:45"/>what is ſinfully evil. Now to be thus prudent and circumſpect in matters of choice in the general courſe of our actions, What a comfort is it to a man, to be followed with the joyful whiſpers of a well-pleaſed mind where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he goes; to be careſſed by an innocent Conſcience, and continually entertained with a ſweet Reflection upon what he has done? Whereas a man of a cajative diſpoſition, who gives Reins to his Paſſions, and no Bounds to his Luſts, is often put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unmanly Proſecutions, and hurried into abundance of Inconveniences; to gratify his greedy and unſatiable Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, he is frequently tempted to ſuch low-ſpirited actions, which he is aſhamed to own, and bluſhes at them, though no body be privy. To how many inconveniences is a wicked man daily expoſed? And what baſe and unmanly ſhifts is he put upon, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate himſelf out of thoſe difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties wherein he involves himſelf? What
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:35992:45"/>violent paſſions and perturbations are raiſed in his mind? And into what wild tumults of action doth ſin frequently hurry him? How doth it perplex and intriegue the whole courſe of his Life, and intangle him in a Labyrinth of Knaviſh Tricks and Colluſions; ſo that many times he is at his wits end, and knows not which way to turn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? Theſe difficulties, and many more, attend a vicious and irregular courſe. But now, Religion only en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages a man to do thoſe things, which in their very nature contrive his good, are commendable and praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, and adminiſter abundance of ſatisfaction to him when he thinks upon them; it diverts him from every tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaction which confronts the Law of Reaſon, and would diſturb his mind upon an after-thought. In fine, the very purpoſe and deſign of Religion is, to make a Man happy even in this Life, by managing his Concernments ſo, that he may neither be afraid or
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:35992:46"/>aſhamed to think upon what he has done at any time. And what a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſtate is it, to be always at peace within, from the conſideration of a Converſation managed with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian prudence! To lie down and riſe with a mind reſounding thoſe beſt and ſweeteſt Ecchoes, <hi>Well done, good and faithful Servant?</hi> How bravely doſt thou acquit thy ſelf? how manfully doſt thou ſtand to thy duty againſt all oppoſitions? And with what a gallant reſolution doſt thou repulſe temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that bear up againſt thee? This therefore I take to be one great and forcible Argument to a holy Life, That it preſerves tranquility of Mind, peace of Conſcience, as conſiſting of the beſt actions, and the beſt choice.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Secondly,</hi> As Religion condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to a happy Life, prolongs our days, and keeps a calm within our Breaſts; ſo it ſteps in to our Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance at the laſt gaſp, by fortifying us againſt the fear and terror of death,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:35992:46"/>and reviving our drooping Spirits with a ſolid hope and confidence of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencing a bleſſed Eternity. What a thought it is, when a man hath his Winding-ſheet in his Eye, his laſt Knell in his Ear; when he is juſt upon a Tranſlation out of this, into another World, that after this ſharp combat between Death and Nature is over, his Spirit will ſoar aloft, and feed upon the Entertainments of thoſe bleſſed Regions above! That though his body ſhall be deſtroyed with Vermin, yet at the command of the great Creator ſhall be revived, and re-united to its proper Soul, and both live in the preſence of God for ever and ever! I ſay, what a thought is this upon a Death bed! How doth it relax the mind, and comfort all within a man, at ſuch a time, who hath a hope of Heaven upon good grounds? What would not an impenitent Sinner give, when languiſhing, that he could but allay the Storm within, and command
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:35992:47"/>ſuch a ſweet Calm! that he could chide his outragious Conſcience into ſilence, recover his miſ-ſpent time, and dye with a good aſſurance of going to Heaven! Some of us, probably, have viſited ſuch Wretches, who never thought of dying, till juſt within ſight of their Graves: What lamentable moans have they made? How miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly handled by their wronged minds? what ſighs and ſcreeches have the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of things paſt fetched from them? What frightful Ideas have their diſturbed Spirits preſented to them? How uneaſy and reſtleſs, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and even confounded with deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair, and left this World in unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Agonies? Now, as we would deſire, when we lie under the ill circumſtances of a crazy body, and a mortal diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, to be quiet and peaceable within, and wear out our languiſhing hours with a good aſſurance of Heaven, we muſt endeavour to lead holy lives, which alone bringeth peace at the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:35992:47"/>laſt. But here ſome may ſay, This we know already, and there is no ſuch need of repeating it. I confeſs, that I pretend not to inſinuate any thing new, but only to remind men of their latter end, and of thoſe things which belong to their preſent and future peace; and how neceſſary this is, too plainly appears by the lives and practices of many, who converſe here as if they were never to dye; who inſtead of wiping off their guilt by a ſincere Repentance, couragiouſly preſs on, as if they were ambitious of being Heroes in Iniquity; they charge through all the modeſty of Human nature, through all their native ſenſe of a God and a Divine Vengeance, and offer a kind of Violence to Hell, as if they meant to force open its Brazen Portal, and enter headlong into it, before it be ready to receive them. Is it not therefore neceſſary to alarm ſuch Wretches with repeated Lectures of Mortality? To remind them of Death
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:35992:48"/>and Judgment; and what muſt be done by them, if they would dye comfortably, and behold the face of the Judge, Chriſt Jeſus, with comfort? But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> and Laſtly, Rcligion is an indiſpenſable Qualification for Heaven. <hi>Without holineſs no man ſhall ſee the Lord. Though we ſpeak with the tongues of Men and of Angels, and have not Charity, we are but as ſo many ſounding braſſes, and tinkling cymbals. Though we have the gift of prophecy, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all myſteries, and all knowledge; and though we have all faith, ſo that we could remove mountains;</hi> Nay, <hi>though we beſtow all our goods to feed the poor, and give our bodies to be burned;</hi> yet if we are not truly Religious, poſſeſſed with the Spirit of Piety and Holineſs, all this will avail us nothing, ſays the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 13.1, 2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Were it poſſible for a wicked Soul to go to Heaven, it would find nothing there which would entertain it to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:35992:48"/>ſatisfaction. For to uſe the expreſſion of one, Our Souls will continue for ever what we make them in this World. Such a Temper and Diſpoſition of Mind as a man carries with him out of this Life, he ſhall retain in the next: If we do not in a good degree mortify our Luſts and Paſſions here, Death will not kill them for us, but we ſhall carry them with us into the other World; ſo that, I ſay, ſhould God admit us ſo qualified into the place of Happineſs, yet we ſhall bring that along with us which would infallibly hinder us from being happy. Thou Carnal and Senſual Wretch! What Happineſs would it be to thee to ſee God, and to have him always in thy View, who was never in all thy thoughts! To be tied to live for ever in his Company, who is of a quite contrary Temper and Diſpoſition to thy ſelf, whoſe preſence thou dreadeſt, and whom whilſt thou waſt in this World couldſt never endure to think
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:35992:49"/>upon! So that the pleaſures of the other happy World would ſignify nothing to him, who is not ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to take pleaſure in them; for the Employment of that bleſſed place, as it would be unſuitable, ſo unaccep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to a vicious and ungodly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. It is therefore the greateſt and moſt powerful Argument imaginable to the Study and Practice of Religion, that it qualifies us for the Enjoyment of God, and renders us capable of the Employment and Converſation of Heaven; it makes us of the ſame Temper and Diſpoſition with God, and the Holy Angels; And then what ſweet Harmony and Communion will there be, where all are of a mind, and all ſeek one end! Therefore upon the whole, Let us embrace Religion as that which will fit us for the Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the greateſt Good; then when we come to dye, our Faith and Hope will become our Anchor, till both be ſwallowed up in Viſion and Fruition.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:35992:49"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>May God of his abundant mercy grant, that we may ſo live here, that we may not fail of commencing a bleſſed Eternity with Them. And this for Jeſus Chriſt's ſake.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:50"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:50"/>
            <head>THE FOURTH SERMON.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:51"/>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:35992:51"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JAM. IV. 17th Verſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Therefore to him that knoweth to do good, and doth it not, to him it is ſin.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN this Chapter the Apoſtle is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcating many excellent duties, relating both to God and man; to God, that we expreſs our ſelves unto him in all the inſtances of Humility, Reverence, and holy Fear; to our Neighbour, that we do not impair his Reputation, nor provoke him by ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings and backbitings; but to do unto him as we would he ſhould do unto us: And, as the Concluſion of this his Diſcourſe, he reminds thoſe to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:35992:52"/>whom he writes, and by them, all Chriſtians, how nearly it concerned them to practice what they heard and knew; and that it would enhance their guilt, and render them the more inexcuſable, if they lived in the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of that which they knew to be their duty; <hi>to him that knoweth to do good, and doth it not, to him it is ſin.</hi> By which, the Apoſtle gives us to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, That Sins againſt Knowledge induce a Crimſon guilt, as being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted with Conſent and Approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For that which maketh Sin to be ſo, as it ſtands condemned, and threatned with Eternal Puniſhments in the Goſpel is, the doing of that which God has interdicted, which we know is in oppoſition to his Holineſs and Purity, when our Reaſon forbids the action, but yet we commit it, to pleaſe a fooliſh Humour, to gratify a rude and ungovernable Appetite. Upon which account is that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Thou ſhalt be juſtified when thou ſpeakeſt,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:35992:52"/>and clear when thou judgeſt,</hi> Pſ. 51.4. implying, That when God paſſes Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Eternal death upon wicked men, they ſhall be ſo far from taxing him with exceſs of rigour, that they ſhall confeſs, to the Vindication of his Juſtice, and the Aggravation of their Shame, that they are deſervedly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. Sin becomes of a damning nature, becauſe it is not only a Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of known Commandments; but an outrage upon our Reaſon, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Faculties, which God has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued us with, to diſtinguiſh between right and wrong, good and bad, that we may chuſe the one, and refuſe the other. It would indeed look more like rigour in God, ſhould he hold us guilty for doing thoſe things which we are ignorant are evils, though they be, and he has denounced againſt; becauſe it is not, properly ſpeaking, a Tranſgreſſion againſt Knowledge, which extenuates the Crime, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes our perſons. For even among
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:35992:53"/>our ſelves, if one ignorantly offendeth us, is neither moved by prejudice, nor a malicious Spirit, propounds to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf neither the pleaſure of revenge, nor any thing that looks like deſign; we cannot, unleſs too cholerick and unreaſonable, but forgive the Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and bury the default in Oblivion. And upon this ſcore it was, that the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> quieted himſelf, in ſome meaſure, under the uncouth Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon his former outrages a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and the Chriſtian Church, 1 Tim. 1.13. <hi>I was,</hi> ſays he, <hi>before, a blaſphemer, and a perſecutor, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious; but I obtained mercy, becauſe I did it ignorantly.</hi> And we read in the 19th of <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> ver. 4, 5, 6. that God extenuates the guilt of an ignorant Murderer, by appointing him a place of refuge; <hi>This is the caſe of the ſlayer, which ſhall flee thither, that he may live: whoſo killeth his neighbour ignorantly, whom he hated not in time paſt; as when a man goeth into the wood
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:35992:53"/>with his neighbour to hew wood, and his hand fetcheth a ſtroke with the ax to cut down the tree, and the head ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth from the helve, and lighteth upon his neighbour, that he die; he ſhall flee unto one of thoſe cities, and live: leſt the avenger of the blood purſue the ſlayer, while his he art is hot, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take him, becauſe the way is long, and ſlay him, whereas he was not worthy of death, in as much as he hated him not in time paſt.</hi> But when the evil is pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, and the precept plain; when Reaſon comes in, and forbids the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; In fine, When a man is conſcious that ſuch and ſuch a commiſſion thwarts the Law of God, and of his own mind, and yet breaks through theſe Barricadoes to gratify his ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born and inflexible will; he is without excuſe, his guilt is enhanced, his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption unpardonable without a ſpeedy and proportionable Repentance, and will inevitably ſuffer the direful effects of an unappeaſed Vengeance.
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:35992:54"/>For it plainly argues, that an evil is done with the conſent and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the will, when a man, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his knowledge thereof, and his modeſt nature bluſhes at the ſenſe of the Thing, and all his Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Faculties, whereby he aptly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhes between Right and Wrong, ſtep in, and forbid the action; I ſay, when a man doth any evil againſt ſo much Light and Knowledge, it ſpeaks much guilt, and matter of choice too, becauſe he knew the Sin, and againſt all oppoſition yielded thereto. And this is it that will ſhame and condemn wicked men in the Day of Judgment, That they allowed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the practice of thoſe things, which, before they could commit them, were with delight fain to give their Conſciences gaſh after gaſh, till by repeated blows they had rendered them callous, and paſt feeling: Or otherwiſe, it would be almoſt impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that Sinners could delight in the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:35992:54"/>ways of Death, that they could laugh and be merry while going in the broad way that leads to deſtruction, if they did not in the firſt place lull Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence aſleep, which, if permitted to ſpeak, would make them very uneaſy, interrupt their paſt-time, and plague them with horrid Thoughts and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections; hence is that of the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.4. <hi>God is not in a wicked man's thoughts;</hi> that is, he will not ſuffer himſelf to think of God, whom he offendeth, nor of the evil he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth, nor of that place of to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which awaiteth him; theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations being extinguiſhed, render his Life much more ſeemingly pleaſant and comfortable. But I proceed to the further Proſecution of my Text; <hi>Therefore to him that knoweth to do good, and doth it not, to him it is ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From which words, I raiſe theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Propoſitions;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the knowledge of a ſin improveth guilt, and leaveth a man without excuſe.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:35992:55"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That man is ſet out in the World, furniſhed with ſuch Faculties which are capable of diſtinguiſhing between good and evil, right and wrong; whereby he may be acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the good enjoined, and the evil interdicted.</p>
            <p>I begin with the former of theſe two, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the knowledge of a ſin improveth guilt, and leaves a man without excuſe; that is, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that ſuch a thing is really an evil in it ſelf, forbidden by God's Law, condemned by our own Reaſon, and threatned with Hell-fire; and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this ſenſible conviction, to proceed to action, induces a crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon guilt, and renders a man, as inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable to his own Mind, ſo to God alſo. For what can be a greater Argument of contempt of the Diſcipline and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Religion, and what can expreſs more a preſumptuous will, than
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:35992:55"/>to do that which I am not only taught by the Word of God, and the practices of good men, is ſinfully evil, but aſſured alſo by my own Conſcience? And though, if we be ſo charitable to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture, that a man doth not commit a ſin, becauſe God has interdicted it, and himſelf diſapproves of it, mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his reaſon, but purely to pleaſe a fond humour, and an irregular appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite; yet this demonſtrates how little regard he has to a divine precept, how light he ſets by Goſpel-prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, thus to prefer a fooliſh luſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a vertue, the ſatisfaction of his own will before his who is to be the Judge of Quick and Dead, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder of good and bad men. And though ſome, the better to colour their evil diſpoſition, and to take off the rigidneſs of cenſuring, plead natural weakneſs and infirmity, that though they are convinced of the evil they allow themſelves in, yet they cannot withſtand the temptation, and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:35992:56"/>reſiſt the inticement; yet this alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains the bent of their hearts, and the prevalency of their corrupt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, and their unwillingneſs to oppoſe the violence of their uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trollable will: for were they really concerned for their unhappineſs, as they ſeem to be; did they make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of committing of evil, as they pretend, they would ſtudy arguments, inculcate reaſons, hold diſputes, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon together the auxiliaries of Nature and Grace, Religion and Reaſon, to back them in the encounter; they would uſe ſpecial arts and ſtrengths of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, pray often, faſt frequently, abſtain from the appearance of evil; which are the means our Saviour pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes as proper to confront the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions of Satan, the temptations of the world, and the luſtings of the fleſh; and which the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> recommends to us from his own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; <hi>I labour,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to bring my body under, that it may be obedient
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:35992:56"/>to the Spirit.</hi> Would a man that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees a danger approaching him, and that unleſs he uſes ſome ſpeedy preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he will inevitably be ruined by it, ſtand ſtill, and ſuffer the damage, when it is in his power to preſerve himſelf? Would he not rather plod and contrive, contend with difficulties, and conſult an eſcape, if he were in his wits? Would he ſuffer the Notion of natural impotency to divert him from endeavouring to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew his Deſtruction? And the caſe is much the ſame; when an Evil preſents it ſelf, and the man has an averſion to it, would he not invent means to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand its proffers? for this is Argument ſufficient againſt it, that he hates the very thoughts of it; for thus holy <hi>Joſeph</hi> replied, when <hi>Potipher</hi>'s Wife im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned him to violate his Chaſtity with her, <hi>how can I do this great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> It was not only the awful appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion he had of God, which withheld him from complying with her inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting inticements, but the abhorrence he had of the Evil it ſelf.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:35992:57"/>
            </p>
            <p>And in this ſenſe the Scripture un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands Converſion; when a man by Conſideration and Watchfulneſs, by ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Prayer and Abſtinence; by certain Propoſitions, and ſevere Reflections on himſelf, has brought things to this paſs, that he not only abſtains from ſinful actions, but contracts an abſolute ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt them; when he hates evil for evil ſake; And this, without all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy, is the beſt and ſureſt defenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive againſt all wicked allurements; for doubtleſs many, who not having ſtrictly obſerved the Diſcipline and Conſtitution of Religion, that is, refrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only from the overt-act, but have maintained a love for, and a deſire after ſome certain evils, have been betrayed and ſeduced to ſin in the action; for outward Religion, without an inward Converſion, is not Argument enough againſt a Relapſe, ſays St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 2. ult. <hi>he's not a Jew, who is one outwardly, neither is that Circumciſion which is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the fleſh: But he is a Jew, who
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:35992:57"/>is one inwardly; and Circumciſion is that of the heart, and in the ſpirit, not in the letter, whoſe praiſe is not of men, but of God.</hi> Hence therefore are theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts inclucated; <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, with all thy mind, with all thy ſoul, and with all thy ſtrength;</hi> that we preſent our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies a living Sacrifice, holy, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto God; that we be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our minds; <hi>that we put off con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the former converſation, the old man, which is after the fleſh; and that we put on the new, which after God is created in righteouſneſs, and true holineſs:</hi> In fine, <hi>That we deny all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world, looking for that bleſſed hope, and the glorious appearance of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; who gave himſelf for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and purify to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a peculiar people, zealous of good works.</hi> But furthermore, there can no
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:35992:58"/>other reaſon be given, why a man commits an evil which he knew to be ſo, and which God had forbidden, but that either he reſolved to come at, and enjoy the ſin, though he broke through never ſo many Barricadoes; and this can be nothing leſs than a horrid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Lawgiver; or that he could not withſtand the impetuouſneſs of his rude inclinations, nor the force of his predominant will; and this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues him of the number of thoſe whom the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, <hi>that their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences are ſeared as it were with a hot iron</hi> It is the determination of the Goſpel that he who knows his Maſter's will and prepares not himſelf to do it, ſhall be far more ſeverely puniſhed than he who is ignorant thereof, and does not fulfil it; for this is the aggravation of his guilt, and the improvement of his crime, he knew his duty, but preſumtuouſly neglected it. And we obſerve that when habitual ſinners come to di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if then they have any ſenſe of the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:35992:58"/>condition, or conſider the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Judgment to come, to which they are haſtning, the accuſation they then bring againſt themſelves is, That they have committed many evils a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their knowledge. They lived in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperately, accuſtomed themſelves to ſwear and blaſpheme, to commit adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, to prophane the Sabbath, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure their neighbours, and ſuch like; theſe were ſins they knew to be ſo, and that God had prohibited them upon pain of damnation; but notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this, they preſumptuouſly allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves therein. And it cannot but be a very uncouth reflection to conſider, that though they knew they were in a ſtate of damnation, yet would not retreat, but have continued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to the laſt hours of their life. But enough for the proof of the firſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, namely, that the knowledge of a ſin improveth guilt, and leaves a man without excuſe, who knows to do good, and does it not; and to him it is ſin.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:35992:59"/>
            </p>
            <p>From this I proceed to the ſecond Propoſition, which is,</p>
            <p>Secondly, That Man is ſet out in the world, furniſhed with ſuch faculties as are capable of diſtinguiſhing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween good and evil, right and wrong, whereby he may be acquainted with the good enjoined, and the evil neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected; this requires no great proof, becauſe our own experience evinces us, that we can judge and determine, and make a true diſcrimination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween things; that we can conſider and make reflections, applaud and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn our ſelves, when either we have wiſely done that which is good, or fooliſhly and unadviſedly committed that which is evil. We often perceive hopes of joy within our breaſts, when we can anſwer our proſecutions; and are apt to bluſh, though no body ſees when conſcience calls us to the Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to hear our Indictment; and thus we become our own Judges, either ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, or condemn our ſelves; and this,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:35992:59"/>becauſe we are capable of knowing good and evil, and have reaſon to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us in chuſing of the one, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing of the other, and therefore it is that we become accountable alſo here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, as the Apoſtle expreſſes it; <hi>We muſt all appear before the judgment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeat of Chriſt, to give an account for what we have done in the fleſh,</hi> and to receive <hi>according to that we have done, whether it be good or bad.</hi> And in regard that God made us rational and conſidering creatures, he has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed certain Laws to obſerve and keep, and by theſe he alſo intends to judge us, that is, whether we have obeyed or violated them, he having ſuited his Commandments to our ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, which are able to diſtinguiſh between good and evil, right and wrong. And therefore by way of exprobration, How wretchedly does Man degrade himſelf, while he acts in oppoſition to his reaſon, and allows himſelf in thoſe things, which his own
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:35992:60"/>mind diſapproves of, and condemns! How inferior is he to the beaſts? they act according to ſenſe, they move in their ſphere, and what they do is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to their nature and being. But when Man by the order of his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior faculties is directed to good, he commIts evil; as he does that which he cannot give a good account of to himſelf, ſo he acts contrary to his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nature, and the knowledge he has of things; for by the very deſign of his conſtitution, he knows what is good, and what is evil; and that the former is beneficial, and the latter hurtful unto him. And how inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble muſt he needs be, that all the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which is done unto him, he did it himſelf, and was conſcious thereof, when he tranſacted it? And this is it which will vindicate the Divine Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in paſſing ſentence of eternal death upon wicked men, That they are condemned for doing of evil which they knew was ſo in it ſelf; and reſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of good, which they alſo knew
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:35992:60"/>was really ſo. It generally prevents men from pitying one who wilfully and wittingly worked his own ruin, when it was in his power to have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided the miſchief; and ſo ungodly men ſhall go off unpitied in the day of Judgment, becauſe they might have obtained mercy, but would not. It will be an ill plea in the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſay, That we did not conſider what we did; that we lived without care, without thought, without ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; for this is not an allowable plea for a reaſonable creature, much leſs for one who knows he muſt be judged: for why did you live without thought, without conſideration? Had you not the power of thinking, of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, of conſidering? And did not God give theſe powers and ſaculties to you, to direct and govern your lives? Did he not make you reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that you might conſider, and live by reaſon? And is it any excuſe then for a reaſonable creature, that he
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:35992:61"/>lived and acted without reaſon, and a wiſe conſideration of things? This is the great degeneracy of humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the abuſe and corruption of thoſe natural powers which God has given us, the ſource of all the evils that are in this world, and therefore can be no excuſe. And this ſeriouſly layed to heart, muſt needs make men have a ſpecial regard to their diſcerning fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and that ſince they muſt be judged, and that is to give a reaſon for what they do, to conſider what reaſon to give, before they do it. And this leads me to draw ſome practical and uſeful inferences from what has been ſaid, and ſo come to a Concluſion.</p>
            <p>And here,</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, it is true, That <hi>to him that knows to do good, and doth it not, to him it is ſin.</hi> What a woful reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will thoſe Wretches have, who here live without care, thought, or conſideration? Who, that they may come at and enjoy their Luſts, lay aſide
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:35992:61"/>their reaſon and underſtanding, that they may not be diſturbed in their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious enjoyments, nor plagued with uneaſy reflections. What a ſad conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration will it be at the hour of death, when all arguments to, and opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſin ceaſe, that they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed themſelves in the practice of thoſe things which they are now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of, and condemn, as diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to rational Creatures, and ſhould heretofore, had they but given way, ſuffered their diſcerning faculties to have interpoſed, and given judgment before they had paſſed into action? It ſeems a Paradox, that man, who has a right notion of Good and Evil, that the one is profitable, and the other miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous unto him; that he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe his comfort, and court his own mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, by withſtanding the Good, and embracing the Evil: In fine, that he ſhould do that which he cannot give a ſufficient reaſon for to his own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and if it be ſo, How will he be
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:35992:62"/>able to ſtand in the great Aſſembly of Angels and Saints, before the Judge Chriſt Jeſus, to render a reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſo often drank to Exceſs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Adultery, prophaned God's Holy Name by Oaths, Curſes, and Imprecations? Why he lived in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> obſervance of his Sabbath, and offered contempt to his moſt righteous Laws; Why he omitted known Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and committed as palpable Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſes: In fine, Why he hated re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, and caſt God's Holy Word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind? How will Wicked men be able to ſtand in the Judgment and anſwer to theſe things? Sometimes Sinners are here ſadly put to it to invent excuſes, to inculcate arguments, and raiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, to extenuate their guilt, and obtain a favourable judgment; they are forced to endure many ſhameful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats, falſe colours, and looſe dawb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with untempered Mortar, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent contradiction and diſcovery: But in the day of Judgment ſuch pleas will
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:35992:62"/>not be admitted, nor need they then endeavour to conceal their Villanies; for all things <hi>are naked and open to him with whom we have to do; he knows our down-ſitting and up-riſing, he underſtands all our ways;</hi> he enters every <hi>Item</hi> of our guilt into his Debt-book, with the purpoſe to bring every Evil into Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether committed publickly or privately; and this conſidered, What a forcible argument is it to be careful, thoughtful, and conſiderate, to examine wiſely, to judge prudently, and to give a good reaſon for what we do before we commit it; in all our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, to call in the Auxiliaries of Nature and Grace, Religion and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; in fine, to do thoſe things appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of by our more refined Faculties, and to omit thoſe which they condemn? Such a wary Converſation as this, would adminiſter much ſatisfaction to our Spirits, defend us from many Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Miſchiefs, produce a comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Death, and a joyful Reſurrection.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:35992:63"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> It is a pleaſant conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That God has created us Rational Beings, capable of knowing Good and Evil, of contriving our ſafety, and ſhunning our deſtruction; What a comfortable thought is it, that we are not meer Machines, moved and actua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted only by Senſe, like the brute Beaſts; but underſtanding, thinking, and conſiderate Creatures, that can judge of the nature of things, debate and examine, before we approve or diſapprove of them! Let us then live like ſuch, eſpecially conſidering that we muſt give an account how we have uſed our Talents, what improvement we have made of our Faculties, and what we are the better for being fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with ſuch large capacities. They were not given us merely to be uſeful in our ſecular buſineſſes, but to help us to the knowledge of God, of our ſelves, and of thoſe things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to our Everlaſting peace; that we may rightly underſtand our duty, and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:35992:63"/>diſpoſe our ſelves to ſerve him accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably, with reverence, and godly fear. We rather abuſe our Natural Powers, when we only imploy them in plod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and contriving about worldly matters; their proper buſineſs is, to ſearch after truth, to find out the way of the Kingdom, and to remove thoſe impediments which retard our ſpiritual warfare, and hinder us from bringing our holy concernments to a happy and comfortable concluſion.</p>
            <p>Let us then bend all our powers this way. Are we rational Creatures? Let us be able to give a good reaſon for a thing before we do it; this will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our Judgment hereafter more feiſible, and leſs tremendous, when our Conſciences teſtify that in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity we paſſed the time of our ſojourning here.</p>
            <p>I conclude my Diſcourſe with that Collect of our Church: <hi>We beſeech thee, O Lord, to grant unto us the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:35992:64"/>to think, and do always ſuch things as be rightful, that we who cannot do any thing that is good without thee, may be thee be enabled to live accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy will, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To whom, with Thee, O Father, and the Ever Bleſſed Spirit, be given all Honour, Praiſe, Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, and Obedience, now, henceforth, and for Evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:35992:64"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
